<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alban Siffer</title>
    <link>https://asiffer.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Alban Siffer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://asiffer.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Desktop Elements Detection Using Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/desktop-elements-detection-using-deep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/desktop-elements-detection-using-deep-learning/</guid>
      <description>Notes
The original post (written with Joseph Paillard) has been published on the Amossys blog. Here, some elements related to the Amossys company (and not paramount on this blog) have been removed.
  Prediction sample 
Context This project has been carried out as part of the AI &amp;amp; Cyber challenge that took place during the European Cyber Week (ECW) 2020. This year, the challenge was to emulate human behavior on a computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse ssh tunnel</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/reverse-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/reverse-ssh/</guid>
      <description>In this post we explain a way to connect to a remote machine behind a NAT with a reverse ssh tunnel. Here we use a third party server as we assume that both local and distant machines are not publicly available (neither public IP nor port forwarding).
Because of NAT, we must first set-up a tunnel between the distant server and the proxy. The proxy is running a ssh server listening on port 22000 (we can connect to it with username user and a secret password):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passing numpy array to shared library</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/numpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/numpy/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Imagine that we have developed a C or C++ (or rust) library which does some operations on vectors and matrices (linear algebra). Without talking about performances, we chose such a language for several reasons:
 System constraints (maybe our initial target does not embed neither java nor python virtual machines) Interoperability with other software (our piece of code if a sub-module of a bigger project) Need to manage memory (yes it happens) &amp;hellip;  Testing such a library is painful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning in Nmap</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/nmap-ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/nmap-ml/</guid>
      <description>Notes
 The original post has been published on the Amossys blog I present some pieces of codes which are originally commented by their authors. I keep authors&amp;rsquo; comments under the format /* comments */ while my own comments use the format // comments. I use the version 7.70SVN of nmap.   First discovery After installing a basic Raspbian on my RPi, I also decided to add nmap to the system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fancy Threat Intel&#39; with Cowrie/MySQL/Grafana stack</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/threat-intel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/threat-intel/</guid>
      <description>We all dream of this world map with cyber attacks between countries like this one or the one of Kaspersky. In this post, we will try to do threat intelligence at our modest level. We will consider a basic system open on the Internet, in the grip of cyber-attackers. In this context, we will collect attacks information so as to make a fancy dashboard to visualize what is going on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribute your work with Git and Launchpad</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/launchpad/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/posts/launchpad/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Let us consider you have developped a nice tool (or a nice library). You make it work on your laptop but, more than that, you put all your code on GitHub of GitLab, for instance. As you are smart, you made a useful Makefile so as to help others to use your work through the famous process:
git clone https://remote.site/mytool.git cd mytool/ make make install However, it looks a bit handmade: of course, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a computer science expert to enter these commands, but this is not as easy as installing an app on your smartphone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a R&amp;amp;D engineer working at Amossys which is a cyber-security company in Rennes (Britanny, France).
I recently defended my PhD thesis (December 2019) which was under the supervision of Pierre-Alain Fouque and Alexandre Termier at IRISA/Inria Lab. I mainly worked on new statistical methods for data mining with some applications to intrusion detection.
Henceforth, I&amp;rsquo;m working on security R&amp;amp;D projects but I also keep on working on my research topics, mainly around unimodality testing and clustering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>My researches mainly focus on statistical learning. As cyber-security is a hard context (high throughput data, lack of ground truth), I try to develop unsupervised methods to mine streaming data.
Publications Siffer, A., Fouque, P. A., Termier, A., &amp;amp; Largouet, C. (2020, December). Netspot: a simple Intrusion Detection System with statistical learning. In 2020 IEEE 19th International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications (TrustCom) (pp. 911-918). IEEE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>https://asiffer.github.io/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asiffer.github.io/software/</guid>
      <description>In addition to the research, we try to cleanly distribute our work. You could find several projects on my github, some debian packages on my ppa and also some python3 packages on PyPI, all with GPLv3 license. Below we detail some of them.
Research related  netspot We have built an network IDS (Intrusion Detection System) upon the SPOT algoritm, called netspot. The idea is to flag extreme events whike monitoring netwrok statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>